hi Freya thanks so much for making time
for this conversation and every now and
then we have these beautiful
conversations catching up on what's
happening with common earth and really
nice to share one of them more widely
and also to give people an opportunity
to know you and your work better and the
amazing work of common earth that you've
been helping to pull together so um I
often start with were just inviting
people to tell a little bit about their
story and and yours is fascinating so
how did you get into feeling passionate
about contributing to the healing of
this earth and and her people like the
the regenerative impulse yeah I mean I
guess first of all I I grew up in a
really rural area of the United States
and in Vermont and I grew up in sort of
an alternative community it wasn't an
intentional community but it was a very
close-knit community um sort of full of
artists and poets my mother is a
musician and a poet my father is a
philosopher and a philosophy professor
and both my parents were you know my
father when we were growing up was part
of the mythopoetic men's movement so you
know I was studying with people like
Michael Mead and and Martine prep Dahl
was sort of active in our community
doing youth initiations and so I yeah
and there was just group of yeah a
close-knit community of these sorts of
mythopoetic types doing theatre in the
woods and storytelling and you know
having bonfires late into the evening
and so I grew up in that sort of context
and then when my parents got divorced my
mother my brother and sister and I moved
to a
were all part of Vermont I mean who ever
lived before was rural as well but we
moved completely off the grid so like we
restored an old farmhouse at the end of
a dirt road and moved to a community
where that was setting up a small
Steiner school so it was maybe 20
families or something and so I also grew
up very connected to sort of my Waldorf
Steiner community and so I spent a lot
of time outdoors and in the woods and
and that I think that connection at an
early age I mean of course then I went
to school and went away to college and I
lost a lot of that but as I got closer
to sort of going thinking about
regeneration it was it was easier for me
to get back to that place because I had
sort of the foundations in which I grew
up were very connected to the outdoors
and yet at the same time I also sort of
when I was growing up it just considered
those topics another subject to study
right wasn't even though I was fully
immersed in all of those sort of
inquiries into the mystic you know my
mother also it was part of a satsang a
community we lived near an ashram and
yeah a community that practiced in the
song tomate tradition which is very
influenced by like in an Indian
spiritual movement that sort of came
into being in the 13th century in India
and was very influenced by you know Sufi
poets and other Indian mystical poets so
I was immersed in all of that but then I
still had this sense of it was just
another thing to study right just
another topic and so in a way my journey
has been to come full circle and realize
that it's not just another topic to
study it's actually a deeper inquiry
into what it means to be human on the
earth and and now that feels particular
irrelevant so anyway that was a long way
of saying that my childhood and some
upbringing how to had a strong role to
play and me getting towards regeneration
even though I have a very
interdisciplinary background and have
not studied science or anything that
full disclosure and probably one of your
less scholarly interviews interviewees a
lot of studying in the last three years
just watching you talk to everybody was
weaving into the common earth Network
that's that's a couple of masters
degrees right there the story you just
told like having a little daughter
myself at the moment I feel like what a
childhood I'm sure it wasn't always easy
and your parents separated it's always
difficult but that connection and I
think the point that you just made of
that really this whole people need to
get that it's about being and practicing
regeneration like it's it's it's it's a
way of being as well as a way of doing
and having had that foundation of
actually living in community and living
with connection to land and and the
wider community of life in in that way I
think is such an important foundation
and also speaks to the importance of
education in the long term creation of
regenerative cultures and how did you
get when so I know that you work in for
quite a long time with this organization
a growing culture and helping like spend
some time in Africa and all that I'd
love to learn more about that
organization and what you did there yeah
yeah so I it was a very roundabout way
of I I was an art history major in
college and worked in the arts arena for
many years and then got really
interested in library science actually
and I have a Masters of Science in
information and library science and well
I was in graduate school I realized that
there were sort of
in the in the library science world
there were two sort of key communities
one was sort of a traditional library
community that was focused on sort of
special collections and books and
museums and I had been very involved in
that community but when I got into
libraries I realized that there was this
other side of the community that was
working around open access and you know
freely available government information
and public libraries because in the
United States public libraries have an
incredible sort of history where they're
these spaces that provide free and open
access to anyone essentially and so
they've been yeah they were very
involved in sort of the social justice
movement and so I got into activism in
library school when I was sort of
training to be a library a librarian and
yeah and it was you know Aaron Swartz
had committed suicide a few years before
I was in library school and that was
still sort of really influencing and
affecting the library community he was
an open access activist sort of trying
to break down the barriers to you know
public access to information of all
kinds because as we know so much of the
information in the world is close behind
peignoir barriers and so forth and so I
got into this sort of activist community
and started to move away from the arts
and I yeah I got a full-time unpaid
internship at the United Nations and
really studied sort of like the
information access channels and ways of
distributing information through
intergovernmental sorts of bodies and
then at that time I reconnected with my
old friend Lauren Carelli who's the
president and founder of a growing
culture and he and I actually grew up
together in Vermont so it was we've been
longtime friends and since I was in sort
of the open access
you know internet hacking sort of
library side of activism Lauren got
really interested in that because one of
the things that he was working on was
how to sort of make the industrial
agricultural complex obsolete in that he
was he's really focused on supporting
small holder farmers and their role in
the food system and their role in
addressing so many of the sort of
interconnected challenges that we face
globally and he wanted to this was in
2015 he wanted to create some sort of
platform or some sort of database where
we could like store and make freely
accessible all of these grassroots
agro-ecological innovations that were
coming from farming communities all over
the world but especially in the global
south where a growing culture was more
focused although now they're doing a lot
of work in the US but and so Lauren and
I partnered up together to work on what
became the library for food sovereignty
right now and Association we we all need
to look at that library yeah yeah it was
and you know of course we we started off
with this idea that would be a platform
and it would it would be high tech and
accessible to everyone and quickly we
got into this process and realized like
that if our main users were farmers in
the global South like they were not
going to use this platform so we
realized right away that it had to be
much more than a platform like this was
about tapping into a community and that
this library was going to be offline and
online it was going to be sort of
transcending many different spaces and
communities and that very importantly it
wasn't sort of this closed database or
like archival repository of documents or
something like that it was this living
and breathing sort of yeah this river of
all sorts of to
and agro ecological innovations from
communities all over the world I think
that is a huge lesson and and kind of
almost message in that story and that I
sit with a lot at the moment when I
watch all these wonderful attempts in
the kind of regeneration of landscape
space where people are building all
these mechanisms for monitoring the
impact of like the regenerative impact
on a piece of land and to help farmers
maybe earn twice not just for their
produce but for the positive impact on
healing the landscape and the carbon
drawdown in the regeneration effect none
of it is wonderful and I'm glad all this
work is being done but but lately I keep
asking myself if we keep doing that all
these the kind of resource economy
people who love the sort of much at
Fresno and Venus Project ilk am I'm
concerned about in the best of
intentions by putting everything on a
platform that is ultimately digitally
digital and you have to have a mobile
phone
or you have to be in that game of being
virtually connected in order to UM to
even engage with this well-meaning
system how we cut out or how we
technologically technologically colonia
lies people who might have actually the
right to choose that they would like to
be smallholder farmers in their
community living in the ways that their
traditions have taught them and not
engaged with those technologies where do
you sit on that double-edged sword of
Technology oh yeah I mean I'm not after
trying to build this platform for
several years I you know don't know how
much I believe in platforms anymore
and yet yeah I mean I think that the big
realization is is that you have to be
you know when you're working on a
platform you're not just working on a
platform you're working on something
much larger and if you can keep that
sort of big picture in your mind then
the platform aspect becomes just one
tool in a larger sort of toolkit to use
so it's not this like end-all like we're
creating this this is the solution this
is going to do it all it's sort of like
let's let's explore and improve our
skills at creating tools and toolkits
that can support in a variety of
different ways but that importantly are
keeping that big picture in mind and
this is like it seems really simple like
keep the big picture in mind but it's
actually really rare that people do
because everyone gets focused on their
one role and the work oftentimes the
becomes about improving and sort of
building that one role instead of
flipping it around and saying how is
this I'm not I'm not against expertise
but like how is my expertise serving
something greater
how is my sort of piece of the puzzle
uplifting the entire the entire sort of
transformational journey that were on
and with with the growing that
particularly in the last couple of years
seeing all these wonderful people that
you're trying to bring together and come
on earth all having this on the ones and
completely
standing like if you build an
organization like drawdown or the
biomimicry Institute or ecosystems
restoration camps or common land and you
you know that they it's doing good work
you know that they're amazing people
working in it that you care about
because you've met their families and
you want to keep them also in the job
and then it becomes understandable that
it becomes difficult to collaborate in
that larger beyond the organization's
actual work because people have that
sort of dual allegiance of yes wanting
to do the work but also not wanting to
jeopardize the work they're already
doing and a lot yeah and it's yeah it's
not like I don't experience that either
you know we all experience that it's
like it's like sort of like we want to
do good work but first we need to take
care of ourselves right and I don't yeah
I don't know how to get around that um
you know I have and then in a lot of
ways it's depressing because it's like
so much there aren't so there isn't
social scaffolding or infrastructure
that allows that uplifts and sort of
supports the transformation that is
really needed and we're all sort of we
have like good ideas in our head and
like the content of what we're promoting
is incredible and yet we're stuck inside
of old business models and nonprofit
structures and we're really trying to
make this leap to something that we
don't we don't even know what it is and
a lot of times I find these structures
are holding us back and I'm also not
saying like that structures aren't
useful I I think institutions and
organizations are useful in some cases
but in other cases they can it can hold
you back um I just wanted to come back
briefly because the the what we were
talking about earlier with the platform
because it reminded me yesterday I had a
conversation with Martin fan Hildebrandt
from guy Amazonas and and he told the
story of how they've been helping in
Colombia to protect and lots of like
over a million hectares actually
the white attire is 16 million hectares
of Amazonian rainforest and for me and
the Jeunesse tribes that live in in them
and have over years fought for the land
rights for these people so they actually
own the the right to their territory and
um in his work or their work with their
wisdom systems of forest management by
living in the forest as part of the
forest and and the whole framework like
he was describing that there and they
still have this richness of the spirits
and the totems and the certain areas of
the forest just being taboo for certain
time times of the year and it's because
of the spirits but it also when you look
at it from a biological point of view
it's because there's some important
reproduction process or growth process
going on so the it's best not to go into
that part of the forest but it's it's
told in different stories that aren't
just the Western rational story and well
I found interesting about it was that
because we are talking about the
double-edged sword of Technology in
these paradoxes and dilemmas we
constantly have to navigate between will
have to embrace and he was saying that
the elders were worried that a lot of
this knowledge was being lost because
when they were putting on three-day
ceremonies the youngsters after a day
and a half were like ok how much longer
is this going to go on and and can I do
something else now and and so the way
that they began to actually engage the
youngsters and rebuild the pride in the
connection with that long lineage and
storyline was to start using some
technologies so they let them make
little videos about the stories and and
and find new ways of capturing that
knowledge in that modern technology way
and while on the one hand it makes me
wince on the other hand I can see well
if that's that's how you make the bridge
between and and engage the next
generation in the value of that
knowledge fantastic yeah I mean I don't
yeah I totally agree I think like the
the objective should not be to sort of
like you know go back to some ancient
way of living but we have to learn to be
sort of of those ways in the sense that
like we need to reposition an orient our
technologies towards something greater
we need to we need to yeah I think live
in relationship with our ancestry and
what's come for us and at the same time
use our technologies as tools to extend
and sort of evolve those relationships
and new ways the problem is is that
technology often comes in and is is not
in tune with those elements right it
comes in and it's it's technology for
technology's sake or its you know it's
part of that never-ending growth sort of
system and so it's not that technology
is the problem it's that it's not being
used in service of something meaningful
so I think that they're almost two
layers to that I completely agree with
what you just said I feel like even when
you get to the layer of being very
cautious and conscious of that it's
still possible that underneath there is
yet one more layer where like trying to
say comes more from from what what Bucky
Fuller's advice and if you if you want
to change the way people think don't
tell them what to think of them the tool
the use of which will change how they
think and I think that with some of the
technologies were using even if we are
using them with the best of intention
for a greater good the tool itself still
has a power of re orientating how we
like what we look at how we look at it
what data we see valuable how it is
processed how we engage with that
situation and that's almost the more
insidious kind of colonialization of the
mind through technology where
and it really takes the practice to
discern how much we all are influenced
by that yeah I mean I'm reminded of you
know like sometimes there's a sense of
like you know capitalism capitalism I'm
me you know extractive never-ending
growth sort of economic system is like
some sort of conspiracy theory or
something to fight when really it's sort
of like worse than that it's like the
logic of a system that's like it's like
the greatest artificial intelligence
that's ever been created right and and
we don't even we don't even really see
it it's like it's like the air we
breathe right and so I'm reminded of
that sort of idea and that we don't know
yeah how that how that technology is in
relation you know is you know in
relationship with our yeah with our
minds and how we how are being
influenced by it
lately I've come to a couple of like
very basic insights like they're almost
so basic that do you feel and with
regard to our the whole capitalism store
because it's the we've had this
conversation before
again this attempt of how do we
internalize externalities and like
social and environmental impact into
this whole conversation in order to
avoid these externalities in order to
give them a place in the mapping and in
the understanding so things get better
yeah it's a it's a well-meaning attempt
but with all these people working on
social capital and natural capital and
all that it's it's also in danger of
becoming a mechanism that actually
monetizes them social relationships and
monetizes the last areas of Commons that
like it could so easily again in
constructing these systems that a soup
to funnel money towards regenerative
practice and large landscape
regeneration and thousand landscapes and
all of that wonderful work but the
danger is that the minute we invent the
conversion rate of these different
capitals into economic capital we're
actually enclosing all of those human
relationships
and-and-and deep wisdom to land in that
economy
and-and-and what the baseline of what
you are just saying that that we don't
really understand that it's the air we
breathe is that simple understanding
that there's the difference between our
culture and all native peoples
everywhere in the world is that we
believed that land can belong to us and
they know that we belong to the land
yeah yes really providing that found and
and to extend that a little bit further
I mean I couldn't agree more I've really
come to also have this really simple yet
profound understanding of the work that
I do and the work that we do a common I
think loud burst and that is that the
real work is working on each other what
you may think we are doing a
regenerative roadmap for New Zealand or
Costa Rica but really we are working on
each other and we are we are learning we
are in developmental learning
relationships with each other and when
all is said and done that those are
going to be the most transformative
aspects and it in the sense that then
the rest will come from that and that
and this is why I I tend to with with
colleagues and like you know friends
around the world I tend to focused first
on a sense of solidarity with that
person and then and then whatever comes
will will come from that place rather
than you know rushing into some work
stream around some good idea without
having established that sort of base of
trust and solidarity with the person
because it's those it's when you rush
into these sort of functional
relationships around good ideas and
there are so many good ideas right
without that connection and I though it
tends to not be as long-lasting and
transformative it's it's a very
different way of working that first way
needs mo use and contracts and and and
financial arrangements and all of that
the second way is a alignment of in
shared intention and and and building
circles of trust that then and you can
get burned with that tool we all know
that but but more often than not you
don't get burned and it and it creates
an agile way of working that doesn't
need all this and yeah fluff around that
takes so much energy and so much
resources and my point is the energy and
deep the the impulse in the world yeah
and again it's I mean I could add
disclosure after disclosure but it's not
to say that mo use aren't useful or that
you know strategy and how strategic
plans aren't useful it's just to say
that if you if you first focus on
establishing a rich culture where people
are there because there is a profound
exchange of value and that you know
they're not there because they're
getting funded to be there or they're
not there because of some vanity play
they're there because they're learning
and because they feel a sense of
solidarity with with what you're working
on between and what they're working on
and then from that you know funding can
if you first established that then
getting some funding will really go a
long way or you know signing that MOU
will be much more impactful at least
that's what I've found and this sort of
brings us right into common earth and
common earth alliance because you know
rulla rulla and Secretary General
Patricia scotland's they've been
convening regularly since 2016 at the
as you know and at our last convening in
October of 2019 Rolla and I realized
that that we could and we should be
doing more than just convening there was
actually this opportunity to sort of
harness our operationalized a larger
movement of a variety of different
organizations and initiatives and
individuals that were working in this
regenerative space and so since then
we've been working on evolving this
common Earth Alliance concept and it's
very we're sort of building it as we go
but it's it feels like it has a lot of
momentum even though there are no formal
agreements there is no funding in place
but what we've been able to do is
establish that sense of solidarity
establish that sense of trust and that
people are coming because they're
learning an enormous amount from each
other and they love the dialogues that
are taking place and I feel like to have
that as a foundation and again it takes
time it's not it's not just like you set
it up in a week or you design it and
then you implement it's a it's an
ongoing process that that the prep that
you and you have to prioritize the
culture that you are cultivating that's
the priority and that's the key it's
interesting because it's like I
I completely agree and um having been
involved in in in varying degrees like
we did much more in the first meeting in
October 2016 and then less so and more
of a kind of listening and feedback in a
little bit of visor II roles since then
um I've been more and more in
opportunities to have these learning
conversations around a wonderful project
that is really worth doing with amazing
people and but we we very often want to
create
inclusive groups with a diversity of
contributions and very often you hear
the voice why aren't there more young
people around this table or where's
where's the global self representation
always the real grassroots present
representation and that's the sort of
shadow side of what you said nobody's
around the table because there's funding
or they get there only there to learn
there is a certain privilege of being
either through trajectory in life stage
like where you're at in your life in a
situation of being able to dedicate X
amount of time to that kind of learning
or non-income-generating collaboration
but what it often does is either really
committed people that have spent all
their life working for grassroots
organizations and haven't built up any
resources to coast on to make time for
those kind of things or young people who
are still not in the process of having
established a way of earning an income
that then freeze them for these
processes they can be quite
time-consuming and because they are deep
learning journeys with a wonderful
community and there's so worth it but
but what I'm but I'm getting it is that
without intending to do so there is a
little bit of selection of a group that
can do this and and there are some
people on the fringe that should be in
the conversation that there are in that
tension of between serving self and
their family and serving the larger
whole that they are also part of of not
being able to engage in the same way and
have you noticed that with what some of
the people that you would have liked to
have involved yeah absolutely yeah not
everyone can be involved in the process
like this and yet I I have over time
gotten used to and have some peace with
the reality that nothing we do will ever
be perfect
and so
another deep wisdom
yeah and that and that actually this
impulse to try to make it perfect to try
to craft the perfect jewel of equality
and the sort of like intellectual yeah
gem of a project or an initiative to
focus on that is to miss the point and
and also to focus on that is in a way to
UM at least I found in my subjective
experience of working on the common
earth is to actually move into a place
in the future or in a place in the past
and not be present in the context
context that we are in right so we you
know and the regenerative movement we
always talk about place source potential
and context and how our efforts need to
be site-specific and rooted in community
and and that's not to say that you don't
at times break down those silos of your
comfort zone in your community and
search for new inspiration and new
perspectives but what I've found is that
yeah trying to get out of thinking in
the past or thinking in the future and
really presencing what is available to
us you know because there's so many
dimensions to a project or an
organization right that aren't just
about the idea right that's actually
like sometimes that's sort of like what
everyone sort of congregates around is
the idea or the vision the mission the
potential and yet there are operations
there's funding there's political
dynamics power structures inherent in
every single effort that we do and to to
sort of tense and shut those out and try
to make it perfect is to in a way not
tap into the true essence of what that
thing wants to be
so yeah I've I resist the impulse to
tried to make common earth this
catch-all for everything like as if as
if we had to do it all in this one
project it had to be the perfect project
you know ticking off all of the criteria
of what a regenerative initiative would
be when it's not possible because we to
work regenerative ly is to reach for
something that wants to be born that is
you know it's it's a process and so it's
yeah you can't just reach for it and
have it be this perfect jewel and then
now you do regenerative development
right it you have to present you have to
tap into the unique potential of the
community you're in and so that's sort
of what we've been focusing on initially
intuitively and now with some sort of
intention that speaks very strongly to
another one of the profound simple
insights that I'm coming back to more
and more is how insidious I got four
years I mean probably I think the first
time I wrote that sentence was in 2002
in my master's thesis at Truman college
and that sustainability isn't an
endpoint that we can ever arrive at but
it's a learning journey in community of
how to participate appropriately in
nested complexity and and yet while I've
rewritten that same statement in many
ways and and and brought it into lots of
my teaching and so on em I still find
that sometimes I fall into the thought
trap of spending time thinking about
some sort of perfect in state and
getting all the pieces of the puzzle in
place instead of really understanding
that that this is a developmental
journey and it will never stop and we'll
never get there
there is no end point that we can then
down tools and say what a wonderful
we've made it it's everything is
hunky-dory because the world keeps
transforming and and and once you really
internalize that
then a you can be easier on holding
differences more likely and still move
forward with with some shared intention
even if one person is kind of a bit
techie new green deal and the other
person is a little bit no no you don't
get it it's all the wrong kind of green
what you're talking about but they're
they're ultimately both people are
people who want to serve positively
moving towards increased health and
wholeness and and they can in the
journey have the conversation because
where we arrive will be neither one nor
the other future it will be who you
won't arrive we'll just continue to keep
learning on the way yeah and
regenerative development is not the new
religion you know that's not the point
the point is not to convince the smart
AG or the you know yeah more sort of
green tech a movement that regenerative
development is what they should be
working on as if it was a different just
another topic or just you know or the
new religion but yeah and and so I found
that just the a key a key part for me in
this work is being able to hold
coexisting different perspectives at
once and just increasingly sort of
increase my own capability as an
activist to hold yeah coexisting and
opposite and polarizing ideas all sort
of at once and give them a seat at the
table almost in your in your thought
process and your in your planning
processes because I think we would all
agree that like none of us really
believe in linearity anymore and even
the you know the guy sitting across from
the table that's you know working on
climate smart agriculture or whatever
like yeah he we don't actually know the
the effects that his work will have on
our work
yeah like you know extinction rebellion
and sort of movements that are more sort
of protest focused on you know peaceful
civil disobedience you could on one hand
say well they're taking a negative sort
of problem focused approach where iam in
the regenerative community is you know
we try to work from place source of
potential right where I'm sort of a very
uh sort of positive optimist and that
lone hopeful at least movement that's
looking for sort of deep transformation
but not sort of picking out all the
problems and working at problems and yet
we don't we don't actually know the role
that some of those civil disobedience
maybe they're probably they're actually
raising the bar and the collective
consciousness around this work that
creates the conditions that allows our
work to be successful so if we get
caught in this oh that's not the
approach I would take or what's that
guy's problem like he's doing then yeah
then we could we don't know because you
know we don't know what effect that will
ultimately have which is why I really
try to focus and embody and live by the
you know growing my own capability and
capacity to hold coexisting and diverse
perspectives in every moment basically
yeah no I completely hear and that the
day's the essence of working regenitive
like the the a like for example even
just but sticking with exile briefly and
they from last year to this you have
already made a significant change in the
languaging from where the key words were
extinction rebellion and rebelled for
life and two more regenerate 2020 and
much more
I love extinction rebellion and I wasn't
trying to kill them no no me neither
like I am so grateful that they've
actually included regenerative cultures
as one of their principles and
regenerative culture and while they're
still dancing with is this just the
culture that how do we support ourselves
in our activism and non direct action
non-violent direct action and and in in
raising the movement and and and taking
care of the movement or is it actually
but I think the regenerative cultures is
actually the answer of how we stop this
extinction crisis and avoid runaway
climate change and and and and the
breakdown that everybody now seems to be
so focused on that we're almost calling
it in um if if we don't leave the
possibility of working a miracle that
back door open and I mean I would love
to share with you just briefly something
that that really you know how that this
holding rather than falling into the
paradigm shift we need to go from this
kind of thinking to that kind of
thinking and in trying to force people
along on the journey the the holding the
polarity between different perspectives
the activating in the restraining force
and looking for the potential that there
lies in not saying it's an either/or
these both perspectives in form and in
like for the longest time when when
again wonderful well-meaning people that
I know who are very much into the you
process and Otto shamans work and and
all the working with all these these you
labs all around the world and they were
very often used the ego to equal M
framing um and and it always rang a
little bit to either or for me like that
sort of there in the seed of making that
move ours felt that's not a healthy
relationship to relate to self
and let's not be devil-like I mean ego
has become a bad word and of course in a
certain interpretation of the word we
know why but what we were talking about
earlier as well in a number of different
ones in this conversation is this
tension this polarity that is common to
all life which is being for oneself and
being as part of a larger whole and and
I just wanna share this image pretty
with you because and I don't know is it
and share screen this one I found this
in a linear next to each other way and
have just played around whether to put
it into a tetrad you know try it like
the ego eco dimension of how do I take
care of my family my community in my
place and do my work right here right
now in this place and how do I build the
connection to serving the larger whole
that this place is part of whether it's
my community in this bio region or this
bio region within the biosphere and the
way we resolve that tension is if on
both ends we actually understand that
serving life and but as a keystone
species like because that another danger
of this ego eco framing for me is either
you deny the importance of self-care and
you will not be able to serve your
community and the planet if you can't if
you don't serve yourself and your family
mmm but also in getting lost in just
serving they like their and I've lost my
my train of thought right now and I had
the the subsuming into Eco of oh yeah
we're human beings were so wrong with we
just have to be part of the web of life
and and be humble little critters in it
m is is not speaking to the potential of
human beings it's not speaking to the
the fact that we can actually and that
now that we have fucked up the system so
badly on so many levels we have the
responsibility
to become healers and keystone species
and nurture health and resilience and
abundance and and increased by
productivity and again it's an ancient
wisdom and that like buddy what do you
think about this resolution well yeah no
I think it's ancient wisdom and when
sometimes people you know when we talk
about ancient wisdoms and having you
know going back to people think that
it's like we're suggesting we go back to
that and and really it's not about going
back it's being from being of that and I
was reminded by what you said earlier
you know how you have these sort of is
profound like realizations on something
and usually when you have a profound
realization on something it's some it
feels like you're remembering something
that you already knew and it's very very
simple and in a lot of ways it feels
like you're going back to and that's
what awareness is right awareness
happens instantaneous realization of
something that has always been there but
now you're fully understanding what it
what it means and I I actually think
that probably transformation is similar
to that like I sort of have this idea
and maybe I got this from Krishnamurti
I'm not remembering a horrible
attribution
but I but you know this idea that yeah
transformation is instantaneous it will
happen like that which sort of for a
rationalist you know mind is hard to
wrap your head around right there's so
much to do right we're so far away from
transformation there's there's so much
work to be done it needs to be done so
quickly and yet we just really don't
know what's going on
and that's increasingly clear I mean
people's lives are changed overnight you
know you can have a conversation with
someone you know lately and this new
science of kovat have been feeling like
people that I've never even met in
person I'm all the sudden like deeply
connected to in very little time and and
so yeah I just not to get all no weird
but they I just I feel like the
timescales there are so many different
timescales on how this is playing out
and transformation I think we're just
beginning to comprehend what that could
mean right now we feel like
transformation means change and change
requires a lot of work but that idea of
change being a lot of work is also
coming from that sort of industrial
mindset right that that a big problem
requires a big response and it's gonna
be a huge undertaking I completely
resonate with that and it brings me to
there's two things that I would
definitely still want to cover and one
of them is I want to learn more about
the Alliance that you've been building I
know who's involved but it would be nice
to hear you share share it and but the
other thing is which which I did we've
talked about between ourselves before
and which I think he also - like I've
heard it what you just said landed in me
in that way is that really this tension
between like I you know I use the word
glocal a lot and working locally like
how do you where you put your energy of
being truly rich generatively in place
changing your being state having more
connection with your community your land
and taking the time for rituals of
connection with people in place and and
really practicing this how do I
contribute to the next greater whole in
in a daily way in your bio region and
then the other thing is connecting all
the good people that are coming into
that way of being all over the place all
over the planet and enabling them to a
feel part of other of an emergent
movement that more and more people are
coming home to a place that more people
wanting to Rhian habit
they're bioregions and and become
healing presences in community and
ecosystem and I personally find that I
live an enormous tension in in that
where do I put my energy because when I
listen to either of people that have
very strongly focused on either of the
those scales the very local or the
global connecting it's so deeply
important work both of it and and
somehow I think we need both em but I
get lost in terms of my own capabilities
in terms of time and energy and yeah
you're it just means you're paying
attention yeah of course you're lost
we're all lost you know it's it's it's
really challenging to live and to live
in these two two to fully be yourself
and support you know regeneration at a
family scale and a local scale and a bio
regional scale and then also be working
on the global side so to to think that
that would just somehow be easy is a
total illusion right and but I would
just encourage us all to to also like
that we always have this idea if only I
could be in that place then everything
would work out or if only I could you
know I would have only had enough money
to leave my office job and farm the land
then that would be like the real
transformative you know decision and I I
think that that's not quite it I think
that actually transformation is always
available to us in any in any context
and that that feeling of tension and
confusion and being conflicted between
those those are all signs of a healthy
person right so feel encouraged that
you're discouraged because otherwise you
would be numb you know if everything was
going perfect and you know it's almost
like you know those of us who are you
know you think of the
the CEO has just got it all together and
he's perfectly happy great life and it
actually those are the most dangerous I
think you know people in this society
because they're they're completely numb
to the illness in and disease in you
know are in our society in our culture
and they've completely given over to I
think I think again it was Krishnamurti
you know it is no sign of health to be
well adjusted in a sick society right so
and so yeah so yeah honor your
discomfort and yeah lean into that edge
beautiful I mean Paul Hawken just quoted
it it's by some woman author I can't
remember her name this notion of Blessed
unrest that drives so many of us I think
is yeah again it's another thing of
framing what I was saying earlier that
the there's no in destination there is
no perfect to have my cake in eat it
there's mob if only I had all this in
place then I could live happily ever
after it's to just really embrace that
these tensions are part of being in life
and they were part of what's making
things interesting and creative but it
also means sometimes you have to listen
to them and understand what I'm coming
to my personal life right now is to also
say there's a breathing in and out with
these things and like right now I have a
young daughter and if for the next 2 or
3 years I swing more on the side of
planting a food forest and creating a
little watering hole in which I can
welcome my local community to think
about our bio region it's a time where I
can be there for my daughter and do all
the things that are also really
important to really live em and practice
what I preach and and and then to trust
that it's not my responsibility to do
any anything in the sense that that if
this it's a global movement people
pick up the ball and run with it for the
next three years if I if I found less
online and more analogue for a few years
and there's a sort of narcissism in
believing that I have to be in both
areas because my contribution is so
important and like it's also okay to
just disappear for a while and and take
care of the caretakers at least that's
what I'm yeah I I live in a house with
four generations I don't know if you
know this I my tickets my husband my
husband's parents and my husband's
grandparents and a three-story house and
I see you know you know my mother-in-law
has completely given herself to caring
for my children when I'm at work all day
and she also has her mother who's
elderly and is also caring for her and
you just when you're in that when you're
like close up in that reality you know
that like that is seriously
transformative work like it's you know
so it's um yeah we don't we don't know
where the most change is happening and
to try to measure it constantly I think
is missing the point
and I think yeah is there the
regeneration movement is is increasingly
moving towards you know alternative
metrics and ways of evaluating how we
are being impactful and I'm so
encouraged to see so many of my
colleagues that are you know really
thinking about regeneration at a family
scale at a local scale in you know how
well they know their neighbors for
example I mean these are these are
critical dimensions of what we mean by
regeneration and if we are pin sort of
point focused on our professional
contributions to the regenerative
development movement I think
increasingly we will find that that
impulse is part of what we are trying to
move away from and yet it's still so
hard and I struggle with it constantly
so I'm not suggesting one enlightens
already
it helps so much to just voice these
things and also find peers struggling
with the same dilemmas and embracing the
same paradoxes because then I mean
that's the power of circle work and
sitting in a console circle that you
hear other people
voice something that you were starting
to all I was starting to think like am I
crazy I'm a what's going on I need to
and then when you hear somebody else
okay they're struggling with the same
human dynamic it gives yourself sort of
permission to say okay maybe I'm not
crazy no I mean this is what this is
what Regenesis calls second line work in
the sense that it's we we have to hold
each other in this field in order for
the field to to grow and to evolve and
to enter into our collective
consciousness and that's that's why I
always say it's it's this is awareness
building work its solidarity it's work
in solidarity it's make its we have to
we have to sort of build the social
scaffolding and infrastructure that
allows us to do this work and in the end
we are working on each other we we may
think we are you know making the food
forest or you know creating a
regenerative development map and yes
that is one aspect but there is so much
more going on and the more that we can
sort of creatively lean into that
mystery of the lark somebody the unknown
sort of mysterious thing that's
happening that we're all part of I think
the closer I think the yeah the
evolutionary leap that we are that we're
wanting to happen will we'll get closer
to us like Rhonda said we're all just
walking each other home yeah who are the
people that after over the like since
2016 building and these meetings at the
Commonwealth had started with this
impulse regenerative development to
reverse climate change and have gone
into all these transformations
then Commonwealth was created and and
launched last October and now you you're
moving in like even mapped and you've
had conversations where people in the
grassroots end of the spectrum and and
also people political players who are
willing to take their member nations of
the of the Commonwealth em into Road
mapping processes and it's New Zealand
or a non Commonwealth member in Costa
Rica with the leadership of Miller
joining this idea can we pioneer one of
those Roman mapping processes II in in
this mapping in these conversations what
some of the pioneering people in the
world doing regenerative work um who
have you identified that that you will
build this alliance with and and what
are the the the projects that currently
give you most hope that there's this
something transformative is emerging
yeah I mean the the main the primary
people that are involved
I mean Rolla obviously is the mother and
the constant caretaker of everything
that we do have been haggard recently
gave this analogy of Marilla which I
thought was brilliant was that in in
some of the Lama Buddhist communities
that he's part of when a when an
important conference or meeting or
meditation session is taking place there
will be one sort of elder monk that will
that will sit in another room and well
well these ceremony is taking place or
the session is taking place they will be
in a deep state of meditation holding
holding the sorry I'm not a Buddhist and
not very to talk about this but they
will be sort of holding them keeping the
candle alive keeping the fire alive for
the entire for the entire group and role
is sort of like that she's like that's
what she's doing I mean she's doing so
much more but like in her
and you know that that that whatever he
described is actually happening at the
United Nations like people don't lots of
people don't know that but there is it
there is something called the spiritual
caucus of the United Nations and there's
a meditation room at the bottom of the
building where the the big hall that you
always see the Security Council meeting
in and all that when when the Security
Council is in session about the global
crisis there's always people underneath
holding the space in that way like
actually meditating and and holding yeah
so yeah so beyond that the we've the way
that we've been evolving common earth
alliances we started with pulling
together a core team so myself or
Alastair Cowan and Haggard Pamela Ming
may East and several others have come in
and out it's sort of an informal
gathering and the core team chartered
the common Earth Alliance so we worked
on what is the what is the purpose and
the role what is the ultimate end state
vision that were that we're moving
towards and so the core team chartered
that and we've we've adopted this sort
of structure that Pamela Ming and the
Regenesis folks introduced to us called
core team task team field team and
essentially it's a very flexible
structure that is designed to support
emergence so the core team is sort of
keeping the big picture always sort of
alive and then fields teams form or what
we call working groups in our case
around specific topics mostly in sort of
the infrastructure I'm using
infrastructure differently than we
typically think of it but like you know
big topics like education or
Nantz or gender national scale
regenerative development planning
processes these working groups have
formed and a core team member is is
present in each one of the working
groups and then as these working groups
sort of scope and define the trajectory
of their work as a team task teams
bubble up to focus on specific topics or
deliver a project so the working groups
we've we've launched three key working
groups regenerative finance regenerative
road mapping and a project and a working
group focused on projects and each one
of these working groups is chaired by an
individual so did not not roll over me
basically and so Stuart Cowan is the
chair or the key facilitator of the
regenerative finance working group and
we're 1212 I think there's twelve people
on the finance working group Caroline
Robinson and New Zealand and Edward
Mueller in Costa Rica are sort of
co-chairing and co-facilitating the
regenerative Road mapping working group
and then David Hodgson is facilitating
the project working group and that's
just getting off the ground now so each
and so each one of these working groups
you can see how there's overlap between
the working groups and the core team in
an attempt to foster alignment and
collaboration in service of the you know
the final end state sort of gold and all
of this is rooted in the context of the
Commonwealth so it's not some abstract
thing and the core team has begun a
process of working on what we're calling
a common Earth Alliance project
portfolio and so the working groups and
the core team and the wider alliance
because as task teams bubble up the task
teams also
reach out beyond the working groups and
involved it's it's a very sort of fluid
alive ongoing process and everything is
anchored in this portfolio of projects
and again the portfolio of projects it's
it's very diverse geographically and
also in terms of scale and stages of
development so you have projects such as
Christopher Nesbit's my amount of
research farm in the leaves that's now
scaling and looking at the rio grande
watershed and southern Belize so you
have a watershed scale project and then
you have you know by a regional scale
initiatives ecological mega region scale
initiatives we're working on something
with CARICOM the Caribbean community and
then you have national scale projects
such as what's being brought forward in
new zealand whatever muller is working
on in costa rica and jason 12 to a large
extent as well in australia has seated
on national scale regenerate australia
project i thought that the new zealand
project initially was sort of Auckland
Bay focus is that now moving to a
national scale conversation moving to a
national scale conversation and I've had
a few calls with James Goodhue and
Wellington who's close with Jason Whelan
is working on an urban regeneration
housing project in Wellington so that's
being pulled in but essentially the
national scale we're still we're still
sort of split we're still trying to
understand the role of the road map in
working group in relation to a national
scale effort so it's they're not the
same so Edward Mueller has his sort of
in-country team that he's been evolving
for years as Caroline Robinson has her
auckland-based but now much larger team
and so each one of these groups is
involved with their own sort of process
around thinking about how regenerative
development plays
at various scales ultimately at a
national scale but the common Earth
Alliance regenerative roadmapping
working group this is is still defining
what its role is but it's but it's
probably more of like a thought leader
role and Ana Ana role in you know we've
only had one meeting you have our second
meeting tonight actually but we're also
looking at the role of story in you know
national scale regeneration because a
lot of times framing a story around what
because you know the idea is not to
replicate regenerative technologies all
over New Zealand it's it's much more
about I think fostering solidarity and
hooking it in with national Clinton
processes at a government level so
anyway so there's a lot of territories
to to be explored still but the common
Earth Alliance Road mapping working
group is a group of individuals that are
thinking about regenerative development
at national scales or have been engaged
in some capacity in that in green I just
saw something that sort of ties to a
loop - at the beginning of our
conversation with with a growing culture
and the importance of food sovereignty
and empowering communities in place and
how like the one piece that since since
it is an initiative that through the
Commonwealth Secretariat is actually
linked in to the policy-making process
in an advisory or by to a convening role
and of those 53 Commonwealth countries
plus one Costa Rica em the role of
in abling the political architecture
through really making subsidiarity the
the core organizing principle that
allows to reorganize human patterns and
in a way that they actually sync with
what we've learned from ecosystems and
how ecosystems work and how health is
maintained in in nested wholeness that
we participate in
and that's another one of those
learnings that I'm sort of distilling it
my own life at the moment is that
actually the work on subsidiarity is
hugely important and like we will not
get this process of capacity building in
place to help people in place to
meaningfully express the gifts they can
give to their community in service of
that greater whole which is their bio
region and the planet if we don't also
enable them to really participate in in
the political process in a different way
and make decisions at at scales that
really matter to them and so it's almost
like we need to flip the entire
political process from regional and
national and international scale taking
on really important coordinating roles
but not the the rank and the power that
they have but the rank sort of needs to
be flipped into that it's it's the local
communities that need to be one part is
that conversation at all on the map in
in that process or not I realize it's
very alive and it's we don't have any
clear answers but what I will say is
that we tend to think of capacity
development as like this thing that
needs to happen locally where as
capacity development actually needs to
happen up and down you know nested
scales you know you can't just build
capacity locally and then have a
government not understand
and the value of it you have to you have
to do it at all scales so common Earth
Alliance you know what it's really doing
you keep hearing me say the real work is
working on each other and that's what I
mean by capability and capacity
development we we need to work with each
other in a variety of different ways
up and down nested scales to change the
way that we live and work and approach
problems or potential in the case of you
know regenerative development and so
capacity development that's the goal of
common earth yet not the goal the well
in a lot of ways it is it is a goal is
to be able to collectively in a highly
coordinated way work on capability and
capacity development up and down these
nested scales from a grassroots level up
to a national scale sort of effort and
it happens it's manifested and expressed
in all of these different ways right
it's it's not it's not always expressed
in like an initiative on capacity
building like it's we we organize
ourselves around first principles and
values as an alliance that's why we
charter the Alliance that's why we
Charter the working groups so that the
organizing framework for each for our
for the culture that we develop within
each one of these teams is based on
those first principles of building
capacity up and down nested scales and
that you know that's very rooted in
learning and being open to new ideas and
we actually have started saying
explicitly that these groups are we we
want to cultivate creative contributions
rather than expert contributions right
this is a create fundamentally creative
process rather than an opportunity to
share expertise not that expertise is
you know not valid it absolutely has a
place but when when we're thinking
creatively as a team that's when new
thinking comes
or word rather than getting stuck in a
lot of sort of the old thinking patterns
so anyway you you appreciate the
complexity of this work and nothing is
perfect you know where we're currently
working you know in 2018 when were
involved in the inception and initial
design of the Commonwealth blue charter
that was adopted by the by the than 52
member states of the Commonwealth to
work collaboratively together to protect
the oceans and this year we're working
with the Commonwealth Secretariat on the
living lands Charter which is
essentially the land version of the
Commonwealth blue charter and they are
taking on some of the main sort of
topics that we care about such as
regenerative sustainable agriculture
indigenous knowledge biodiversity you
know water retention sort of technology
is you know agroforestry reforestation
and those sorts of things and so there's
this opportunity to link the common
Earth Alliance project portfolio of
demonstration sites where you can see
these technologies playing out in all
sorts of different ways at different
scales to a policy initiative that is
being brought forward and sort of you
know socialized if you will with the 54
now 54 member states the Commonwealth so
I'm 54 yeah the moldos just joined oh ok
great didn't know that well we could go
on for a long time but we'll probably
should wrap it up so even the most
patient viewers of 90 minutes of
conversation kit and end with it
sometime and the one question I feel
tempted to ask although he's a little
bit in that sort of
the future ideal state a kind of line is
if you had a magic wand right now to
make three wishes for the future of this
impulse that is common earth what's most
needed to make this community of
practice unfold its potential and a
direct asks in terms of how people
engage funding whatever like whatever
comes to mind what what other that the
bits that did you if you say things work
wonderfully in the next five to ten
years where would you see this process
going to yeah well I think you know I I
think you'll appreciate this that I I
really value the culture that we create
you know working together so I put most
of my effort into you know fostering a
regenerative culture with everyone we
work with from a trustee level to
Commonwealth diplomatic sort of levels
to the grassroots community so for me
regenerative culture and establishing
that sense of solidarity is at the
forefront of the way that I approach my
work and I think that when that happens
funding comes it's not a yeah so I and
so I would like to see more financing
being you know brought to these
communities but with a different mindset
it's a it's because it's um it's not
just about getting money to these
projects right we have to we have to
change finance and finance change is
what I've heard the club of room talk
about and so yeah those two are
interlinked quite closely and I think
part of changing finance is it's
connected with changing culture and
working on regenerative cultures so yeah
tuqwan and I also you know magic wand
would also be looking at what is the
overarching political narrative that
these countries take with regard to
climate change and and the other sort of
interconnected global goals this is are
we breaking down silence of thinking are
we are we really sort of moving towards
transformation rather than just trying
to fix a broken system and I I'm still
feeling a lot of like fix the broken
system as I'm sure you are
and so I yeah I hope that we can push
countries to and embrace different
narratives and and stories about what it
means to address climate change it will
happen is happening I think it it's
amazing how catalytic this work actually
is and we'll never see the end of it
will never see the extent of the impact
because it travels like mycelium and
pops up in surprising places so yeah
thank you so much for this conversation
like I think there's there's a lot of
really beautiful points that we
highlighted just through the story of
what we engage with I hope it's useful